# Pingchuan Ma

Massachusetts Institute of Technology Phone:
Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory Email:
Cambridge, MA 02139 Homepage:

# Biography

**Research Interests:** physics-based learning, robotics, generative models.

**Research Goals:** (1) reconstructing efficient realistic physics-based environments, (2) generating intelligent agents upon the environments, and (3) realizing the agents in the physical world.

+1 (617) 404-2333

pcma@csail.mit.edu

https://pingchuan.ma

#### **Publications**

- [1] **Pingchuan Ma**, Tsun-Hsuan Wang, Minghao Guo, Zhiqing Sun, Joshua B Tenenbaum, Daniela Rus, Chuang Gan, and Wojciech Matusik. "LLM and Simulation as Bilevel Optimizers: A New Paradigm to Advance Physical Scientific Discovery." In: *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*. PMLR. 2024.
- [2] Tsun-Hsuan Wang, Juntian Zheng, **Pingchuan Ma**, Yilun Du, Byungchul Kim, Andrew Spielberg, Joshua B Tenenbaum, Chuang Gan, and Daniela Rus. "DiffuseBot: Breeding Soft Robots with Physics-Augmented Generative Diffusion Models." In: *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems* (*NeurIPS*) (2023). [Oral]
- [3] **Pingchuan Ma**, Peter Yichen Chen, Bolei Deng, Joshua B Tenenbaum, Tao Du, Chuang Gan, and Wojciech Matusik. "Learning Neural Constitutive Laws from Motion Observations for Generalizable PDE Dynamics." In: *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*. PMLR. 2023, pp. 23279–23300.
- [4] Tsun-Hsuan Wang, **Pingchuan Ma**, Andrew Spielberg, Zhou Xian, Hao Zhang, Joshua B Tenenbaum, Daniela Rus, and Chuang Gan. "SoftZoo: A Soft Robot Co-design Benchmark For Locomotion In Diverse Environments." In: *International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)*. 2023.
- [5] John Z Zhang, Yu Zhang, **Pingchuan Ma**, Elvis Nava, Tao Du, Philip Arm, Wojciech Matusik, and Robert K Katzschmann. "Sim2Real for Soft Robotic Fish via Differentiable Simulation." In: 2022 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS). IEEE. 2022, pp. 12598–12605.
- [6] Allan Zhao, Tao Du, Jie Xu, Josie Hughes, Juan Salazar, Pingchuan Ma, Wei Wang, Daniela Rus, and Wojciech Matusik. "Automatic Co-Design of Aerial Robots Using a Graph Grammar." In: 2022 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS). IEEE. 2022, pp. 11260–11267.
- [7] Elvis Nava, John Z Zhang, Mike Yan Michelis, Tao Du, Pingchuan Ma, Benjamin F Grewe, Wojciech Matusik, and Robert Kevin Katzschmann. "Fast Aquatic Swimmer Optimization with Differentiable Projective Dynamics and Neural Network Hydrodynamic Models." In: *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*. PMLR. 2022, pp. 16413– 16427.
- [8] Allan Zhao, Jie Xu, Juan Salazar, Wei Wang, **Pingchuan Ma**, Daniela Rus, and Wojciech Matusik. "Graph Grammar-Based Automatic Design for Heterogeneous Fleets of Underwater Robots." In: *2022 International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*. IEEE. 2022, pp. 3143–3149.
- [9] **Pingchuan Ma**\*, Tao Du\*, Joshua B Tenenbaum, Wojciech Matusik, and Chuang Gan. "RISP: Rendering-Invariant State Predictor with Differentiable Simulation and Rendering for Cross-Domain Parameter Estimation." In: *International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)*. 2021. [Oral] (\* indicates equal contribution)
- [10] Tao Du, Kui Wu, **Pingchuan Ma**, Sebastien Wah, Andrew Spielberg, Daniela Rus, and Wojciech Matusik. "DiffPD: Differentiable Projective Dynamics." In: *ACM Transactions on Graphics (Proc. SIGGRAPH) 41.2 (2021), pp. 1–21.*
- [11] **Pingchuan Ma**, Tao Du, John Z Zhang, Kui Wu, Andrew Spielberg, Robert K Katzschmann, and Wojciech Matusik. "DiffAqua: A Differentiable Computational Design Pipeline for Soft Underwater Swimmers with Shape Interpolation." In: *ACM Transactions on Graphics (Proc. SIGGRAPH) 40.4 (2021), pp. 1–14.*
- [12] **Pingchuan Ma\***, Tao Du\*, and Wojciech Matusik. "Efficient Continuous Pareto Exploration in Multi-Task Learning." In: *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*. PMLR. 2020, pp. 6522–6531. (\* indicates equal contribution)

Pingchuan Ma

[13] Jie Xu, Yunsheng Tian, **Pingchuan Ma**, Daniela Rus, Shinjiro Sueda, and Wojciech Matusik. "Prediction-Guided Multi-Objective Reinforcement Learning for Continuous Robot Control." In: *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*. PMLR. 2020, pp. 10607–10616.

[14] **Pingchuan Ma\***, Yunsheng Tian\*, Zherong Pan, Bo Ren, and Dinesh Manocha. "Fluid Directed Rigid Body Control using Deep Reinforcement Learning." In: *ACM Transactions on Graphics (Proc. SIGGRAPH) 37.4 (2018), pp. 1–11. (\* indicates equal contribution)* 

# **Preprints**

- [15] Minghao Guo, Bohan Wang, **Pingchuan Ma**, Tianyuan Zhang, Crystal Elaine Owens, Chuang Gan, Joshua B. Tenenbaum, Kaiming He, and Wojciech Matusik. "Physically Compatible 3D Object Modeling from a Single Image." In: *arXiv* preprint arXiv:2405.20510 (2024).
- [16] Yifei Li, Yuchen Sun, **Pingchuan Ma**, Eftychios Sifakis, Tao Du, Bo Zhu, and Wojciech Matusik. "Neural Fluidic System Design and Control with Differentiable Simulation." In: *arXiv preprint arXiv:2405.14903* (2024).
- [17] Liane Makatura, Michael Foshey, Bohan Wang, Felix HähnLein, **Pingchuan Ma**, Bolei Deng, Megan Tjandrasuwita, Andrew Spielberg, Crystal Elaine Owens, Peter Yichen Chen, et al. "How Can Large Language Models Help Humans in Design and Manufacturing?" In: *arXiv preprint arXiv:2307.14377* (2023).
- [18] **Pingchuan Ma\***, Yao Zhou\*, Yu Lu, and Wei Zhang. "Learning Efficient Video Representation with Video Shuffle Networks." In: *arXiv preprint arXiv:1911.11319* (2019). (\* indicates equal contribution)

### Education

### ${\bf Massachusetts\ Institute\ of\ Technology}, {\bf Cambridge}, {\bf MA}$

Sep. 2019 - Present

Ph.D. in Computer Science, EECS

· Cumulative Graduate GPA: 5.0/5.0

#### Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA

Sep. 2019 - Feb. 2023

S.M. in Computer Science, EECS

· Thesis: Efficient Continuous Pareto Exploration In Multi-Task Learning

#### Nankai University, Tianjin, China

Sep. 2015 - Jun. 2019

B.Eng. in Software Engineering, Software College

- · Outstanding Undergraduate Thesis Award (Top 1%)
- · Major GPA: 93.9/100 Overall GPA: 92.1/100 Ranking: #1/91

# Research Experience

### Research Assistant at MIT CSAIL, Cambridge, MA

Sep. 2019 - Present

Advisor: Prof. Wojciech Matusik

#### Research Summer Intern at NVIDIA Seattle Robotics Lab, Seattle, WA

May 2024 - Present

Advisors: Dr. Jie Xu and Prof. Dieter Fox

### Research Summer Intern at MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab, Cambridge, MA

Jun. 2021 - Aug. 2021

Advisor: Prof. Chuang Gan

# Research Intern at SenseTime Research, Shenzhen, China

May 2018 - Feb. 2019

Advisors: Prof. Ping Luo and Dr. Wei Zhang

### Research Assistant at Nankai University, Tianjin, China

Apr. 2016 - Jun. 2019

Advisors: Prof. Bo Ren and Prof. Ming-Ming Cheng

Pingchuan Ma

# **Professional Experience**

#### **Conference Reviewer**

- · Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)
- · International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)
- · International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)
- · Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)
- · Eurographics Conference (EG)

# Journal Reviewer

- · ACM Transactions on Graphics (Proc. **SIGGRAPH**)
- · ACM Transactions on Graphics (Proc. SIGGRAPH Asia)
- · IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L)

Excellent Volunteer, Nankai University

National Scholarship (Top 1%)

· Computer Graphics Forum

#### **Teaching Experience**

· MIT 6.807/6.839 Advanced Computer Graphics	Fall 2022
Challenges and Competitions	
2nd place for MIT in Citadel Terminal Live: Harvard v. MIT	2020
2nd place in Meitu Short Video Real-Time Classification Competition	2018
1st place in Microsoft Hackaton - Nankai University	2015
Awards and Honors	
Outstanding Undergraduate Thesis Award (Top 1%)	2019
Zhou Enlai Scholarship Candidate (20 out of all undergrads)	2018
The First Prize Scholarship (Top 5%)	2017, 2018

Last updated: June 3, 2024

2017

2016